<?xml-stylesheet href="../common.css"?><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<div class="navbar"><a href="Meg.xml">Meg</a> &gt; Project</div>

<h2>Game Info &amp; Settings Page</h2>

<p><img src="./images/Image4.png" alt=""/></p>
<p>These this were you can change the features of the engine for suit your game. </p>
<h3>Project Settings</h3>
 
Project ID: Unique ID for the current project. Also can be use to allow access it's saved info from other games.<br/>
Project Title: Name of the Game. <em>&quot;project.title&quot;</em><br/>
Project Author: Your name. <em>&quot;project.author&quot;</em>

Debug: enables/disable the debug mode. <strong>&quot;debug.able&quot;</strong><br/>
Audio: enables/disable the audio system. <strong>&quot;audio.able&quot;</strong>

Saving: enables/disable the saving/loading. <br/>
Allow Save Access: Enable to allow other games to access the saved information from this games.

Icon: 32x32 png image used project icon and window icon<br/>
Banner: Banner image used on the loading screens.

<h3>Display Settings</h3>
 
<p><img src="./images/Image36.png" alt=""/></p>

Mode: Select the display systems to use. Note: This setting is currently only used on PC platform.<br/>
Colour Bit: Defines the size of the Colour Bit. O will auto select the value depending on the platform.

Custom Display Dimension: Allow a display dimension interdependent of the Screen Dimension. Display Dimension is analogous to the window size.<br/> 
<p>Screen Dimension: The Area that the game draws to. </p>

Fullscreen: <br/>
Scale Display: Scales the graphics from Screen Dimension to the Display Dimension.

<h3>Miscellaneous Settings</h3>

<p><img src="./images/Image37.png" alt=""/></p>
<p>Map Dimension: The Dimension used for Maps.</p>
<p>Default Language: The language file that the game will use as default.</p>
<p>Number of Player: Number of players that are set up for the game. Maximum of 16.</p>

Graphics Content: Use a pre-made graphics package. (Not implemented yet) <br/>
Sound Effects Content: Use a pre-made sound effects package. (Not implemented yet)<br/>
Music Content: Use a pre-made music package. (Not implemented yet)

<h3>Advance Settings</h3>
 
<h4>Player Controls</h4>

<p><ul><li>control.set1</li><li>control.set2</li></ul><h4>Game Options</h4></p>
<p><ul><li>display.limit</li></ul><h4>Networking</h4></p>
<ul><li>server.ip</li><li>server.able</li><li>client.entity</li></ul>
<h3>Custom Controls</h3>

<p>Player controllers can be change by modify the &quot;control.set1&quot; setting.</p>
<p>Control configuration are store in | separated list. They are stored in this order, Axis 1, Axis 2, Pointer, Button 0, ... , Button 15. </p>
<h4>Axis</h4>

<p>Each axis is three values between -255 and 255 representing x,y,z axis</p>

Predefine Options
<ul><li>arrows </li><li>numpad</li><li>keyboard-wasd</li><li>mouse (not supported yet)</li><li>touchscreen (not supported yet)</li><li>controlaxis </li></ul>
<h4>Pointer</h4>

<p>x/y values of the mouse, touchscreen or controller stick.</p>

Predefine Options
<ul><li>mouse</li><li>touchscreen (not supported yet)</li><li>controlaxis</li></ul>
<h4>Button</h4>
 
<p>Button is a off/on control. Unlike Axis and pointer, you use a prefix followed by number representing the input.</p>

Predefine Prefix
<ul><li>k for keyboard key.</li><li>m for mouse button.</li><li>b for controller button.</li><li>h for controller hat.</li></ul>
<h4>Example</h4>

<pre>
arrows|none|mouse|k97|k115|k100|k113|k119|k101|k13|k273|k274|k275|k276|m1|m2|m3|m4|m5
controlaxisA0|none|mouse|b100|b101|b102|b103|b104|b105|b106|b107|b108|b109|b110|m1|m2|m3|m4|m5
</pre>
<p>Note the A0 after controlaxis, that stands for controller A, axis 0.</p>


</div>